[MUSIC]
Welcome to the module on
Android Concurrency Frameworks.
Although the standard Java threading,
synchronizer, and
coordination features,
covered in the previous module,
provide the foundation for
Android's concurrency mechanisms.
They can be tedious and
error-prone to use, and
don't shield application developers
from Android's design constraints,
such as its non-thread safe GUI libraries,
and
its limits on the amount of time the one
the only user interface thread can block.
Therefore, to ensure the concurrency
can be used correctly, efficiently and
scalably in applications and middleware,
as well as to elevate the complexity of
its design constraints, Android provides
several concurrency frameworks that allow
background threads to run in
parallel on multiple cause.
And communicate in various ways
with its user interface thread.
This module focuses on two
Android concurrency frameworks.
First we cover its handlers,
runables and messages.
Or hammer framework, which provides
a loosely connected set of classes,
that allow long duration operations to run
in one ore more background threads, and
then publish the results of these
operations to the user interface thread.
Second, we cover Androids
async task framework,
which provides a more tightly
connected set of classes,
that executes long duration operations
in one or more background threads.
And publish the results to the user
interface thread without manipulating
threads, handlers, messages or
runables explicitly.
We'll explore the structure and
functionality of these frameworks, and
show how to apply them to
develop concurrent programs.
Such as a threaded downloads
application that implements three
concurrency models using the Android
Hammer, and AsyncTask frameworks.
We also demonstrate how Android
concurrency frameworks are applied to
its middleware and packaged applications.
As well has how its frameworks
are enhanced, by the application of
Gang of Four patterns, such as template
method, strategy, and factory method.
And POSA patterns, such as active object,
command processor, half sync half async,
and threat specific storch.
[MUSIC]